<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Return to the letter of a noble peer concerning the addresses</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57089</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1184</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R36780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16015445</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16015445</idno>
            <idno type="VID">104764</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57089)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 104764)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1155:33)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Return to the letter of a noble peer concerning the addresses</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Ralph Stamp,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London?] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1660-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:104764:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A RETURN to the LETTER OF A NOBLE PEER, Concerning the ADDRESSES.</head>
            <floatingText type="letter">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>My Lord,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>THE Favour you conferred upon me, to permit me to write to your Honour, with a condeſcending Invitation, occaſioned that of <hi>March</hi> the 4th. directed to your hand; in which, my Thoughts of the numerous <hi>Addreſſes</hi> ſeemed to me ſo plainly ſet down, that no Miſtake could enſue: yet it hath otherwiſe happened, and your Anſwer, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though not altogether differing from my Expectation, is not wholly ſuch, nor ſo ingenious, as I expected. I could have wiſh'd, that as you printed the Anſwer, you had with it publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Letter, which gave the Occaſion, that if any Knowledge of the Perſons between whom this Intercourſe is uſed, ſhould give the World occaſion to repeat our Names, and deſcant upon our Judgments, I might not appear, after ſo much reſolute Conſtancy, now dotiſh and fluctuating.</p>
                  <p>But for your whole Diſcourſe, <hi>Noble Peer,</hi> I muſt be plain in telling you, that not I, but the Likeneſs of it to that Speech you made in the <hi>Houſe,</hi> which being publiſhed, the <hi>Hangman</hi> committed to the Flames, hath publiſh'd you the Author: And you do ſo mince this <hi>Aſſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation,</hi> and turn and wind it ſo tenderly, that it ſeems your own Projection, and a Brat ſo taking in your Affections, that every <hi>Abhorrence</hi> of it is a Daggers point at your Heart. You are much in Labour to have it believed never to have a Being, thinking that way to ſecure it from the zealous Abhorrors, and yet at every other turn, your Fondneſs of it makes you break out into Commendations of it's pretty Features and Uſefulneſs. Indeed, your Shiftings ſhew you have ſomething of a debauch'd Modeſty left, and that you are aſhamed of what you ſo much love; my Willingneſs to excuſe what will bear it, ſaith this of you: but the Generality cry out upon your Impudence, in ſaying, <hi>An Aſſociation pretended to have been ſeized in the E. of</hi> S's <hi>Cloſet,</hi> when nothing was ever more exactly proved, nothing more unqueſtionable and free from diſpute, nothing more defended by that Lord's <hi>Clien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,</hi> and even owned in the <hi>Court</hi> by two of his <hi>Compurgators,</hi> (for they acted ſuch more than <hi>Jury-men</hi>) who looking upon it, ſaid, <hi>This is the ſame with that which we ſaw produced, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted in the Houſe of Commons.</hi> And by the way, you may take notice what Juſtice was like to be done the <hi>King,</hi> when his Cauſe was in the hand of Perſons guilty of the ſame Conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy; for, ſhould they have found the <hi>Bill,</hi> they had directed the <hi>Attorney General</hi> to draw up one againſt themſelves; as truly it is to be lamented, that they and all others ſhould eſcape free from Puniſhment, who in the <hi>Houſe</hi> ſaw and promoted this damnable <hi>Plot</hi> of <hi>Aſſociation,</hi> and did not ſo diſcover it, as to have the <hi>Projectors</hi> and <hi>Forwarders</hi> rewarded with their merit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Rope.</hi> The Authors of ſuch <hi>Parliamentary Proceedings</hi> ought to have their Heads advanced to the Houſe-top, to admoniſh their <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of <hi>Modeſty</hi> and <hi>Allègiance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But to return; Your Title, at the firſt ſight, made me merry with the Remembrance of your <hi>Lordſhip's</hi> and that <hi>Religious Party</hi>'s, you ſo diligently ſerved, accuſtomed Activity, that out run their Sagacity, <hi>laying open</hi> dangerous <hi>Plots</hi> and <hi>Deſigns</hi> before they were <hi>detected.</hi> As your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> hath been frequently termed a <hi>Catt,</hi> from your noted Skill in falling ſafely, ſo you further merit it from the Apology of the <hi>Catt</hi> changed into a beautiful Woman, receiving a Change only in Form not in Conditions. You are by the exceeding Greatneſs of Royal Favour, raiſed to very great Riches and Honour, not only out of a mean Fortune, but (pray pardon my Plainneſs and neceſſary Freedom) an ill State (as you are too conſcious) that me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rited Severity: yet all <hi>Indulgences,</hi> all immerited Additions of Luſtre and Fortune, cannot al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter you, but you muſt be <hi>Catting,</hi> ſtill playing your old Tricks, <hi>laying open</hi> before <hi>detecting.</hi> Your Wit hath, like <hi>Galba</hi>'s, very unſeemly Lodgings, and is no other than what may be conjectured to proceed out of ſo ill contrived a Frame, miſchievous and unlucky: it ſerveth to no eminent Counſel, but to impoſe upon the ſilly and credulous Multitude, who adore you as ſome Idolaters are ſaid to chooſe and worſhip their God, for it's excellent Deformity. No Man who makes a juſt and ſerious Inſpection into theſe <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> ſeeth any thing but what becomes generous and loyal Subjects, whom the Senſe of their own Duty, and the odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Practiſes of Men of your Principles, ſtir up to theſe Expreſſions of Fidelity on their own part, and a moſt reaſonable Abhorrence and Deteſtation of the others.</p>
                  <p>And now, becauſe it is an Anſwer to my Letter, you lay upon me the Task of enquiring what this Monſter which you have rip'd up and laid open, is.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:104764:2"/>
                  <p>You begin to tell me, that the <hi>Fermentation</hi> which the Nation is put into, muſt be cheriſh'd by the ways that firſt occaſioned it, and that the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Deſigns againſt the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> and <hi>Liberties</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> would miſcarry, if the Heats and Animoſities between <hi>Proteſtants</hi> were not artificially fomented. Here the Tale you tell of the <hi>Romiſh Deſigns</hi> is ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly ſtale, that it ſtinks abominably, and is rejected by moſt of the apprehenſive Diſſenters and Factious Party, who ſee it in vain to talk any more at that rate, the Generality of the Nation being cured of thoſe Fits which the affrightful Noiſe of <hi>Popery</hi> put it into. For, as ſoon as honeſt and quiet Men hear any begin to blutter thoſe fuſty Diſcourſes, they leave them as men tainted and ruſty, Tools (as you call them) to your Trade of <hi>Proteſtant Joynery.</hi> And the Truth is, you all ſo torment and ſaw what you take in hand to poliſh, that it's great pity the <hi>Maſters</hi> of the Company are not hanged for Company, with the <hi>Journey-man.</hi> It's time indeed ſome end were put to the Lunacy the Kingdom hath been afflicted with, and I hope we may conclude it wrought, or near effecting, ſeeing the greateſt part of what you ſtile <hi>diſtracted</hi> are recovered, and you are found not Lords of the Aſcendent Predominant over Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions, but Witches and Juglers that have held men under ſome ſhort Surprizal, but are deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> Preſident at the Council-Table. Even they who commend you do not believe you, and the reſt will never truſt you: Neither have you ſhot your Bolt any thing near the Mark, in ſaying, the Operation of the <hi>Declaration</hi> againſt the two laſt Parliaments being wholly ſpent, this againſt the Aſſociation is ſlipt in, and managed to <hi>perpetuate Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours;</hi> for your ſelf (I fear to your Grief) find the contrary, both that the Efficacy of the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration</hi> is not ſpent, but hath produced this brisk and genuine Off-ſpring, the natural Iſſue of ſo incomparable a Conjunction as the <hi>Peoples</hi> Affections, anſwering their <hi>Prince's</hi> Conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſion and Love; and that it is ſo far from foſtering Animoſities, that it is the moſt certain Bond of Union that could ever have been framed; a <hi>League</hi> indeed <hi>offenſive and defenſive,</hi> not as your ſquinting Loyalty and unmannerly Compariſon would make it ſeem, between the <hi>Prince</hi> and a <hi>Faction,</hi> but between the <hi>King</hi> and all his <hi>Subjects,</hi> who conſcientiouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect their own duty, and the general Welfare. We never think or call that a Faction, which, compelled by the <hi>Fear of God, honoureth the King;</hi> but you, who of all Men living, have the greateſt Provocations to admire and love regal Clemency and Bounty, do moſt wretchedly, after all the ſtricteſt Engagements to Loyalty, <hi>turn back like a Dog to his Vomit,</hi> and are pleaſed no otherwiſe, but during your Reſpect to that vile <hi>Excreſcence of Government,</hi> which hath been ſpued out and abhorred, as your beloved Aſſociation is now, chiefly for it's Tendency toward the ſame.</p>
                  <p>After you have made a Citation of a Loyal Gentleman's words, you will needs inſinuate from them, a parity of His moſt Excellent Majeſtie's, and that baſeſt of Uſurper's <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Cauſe, and do in effect deride all that out of Devotion worſhip the true God, becauſe ſome, out of Fear or Illuſion, have worſhip'd the Devil. Uſurpers, conſcious to themſelves what Hatred their ambitious and tyrannical Invaſions merit, ſtudy Popularity, and are forc'd to fawn upon the worſt of men, whom they intereſt to impoſe upon others, and always rule by Arts contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Preſcriptions of Legal and juſt <hi>Monarchy;</hi> They either affright or corrupt men to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious acknowledgments; Theſe, with Majeſtical, but Gracious Countenance, receive the due Tributes of voluntary Obedience, and encourage Fidelity, to the ſhame and terrour of ſuch as aſſociate and conſult by their <hi>Kings</hi> to diſturb the Publick Peace. Becauſe ſome un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duely flattered <hi>Oliver,</hi> (once your Maſter) therefore you will allow none to give our Lawful <hi>King</hi> thoſe proper Eulogies and Thanks which his wiſe and excellent Government challenges from all, whom God hath bleſſed with Judgment to ſee and rejoyce in their happineſs by and under him.</p>
                  <p>But this, with your Lordſhip, is <hi>a baſe and deſtructive Deſign:</hi> a ſtrong Affirmation, which you would have received, although you have forgotten to tell us the Reaſon. And ſo in truth you have the Senſe which ſhould direct us to what you mean, in ſaying, <hi>It would have been ſome Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument of the Addreſſors Candour, and ſincerity of their Intentions, in what they did before, if they had forborn their late Applications, till they had found that they were not miſtaken in the grounds upon which they think to vindicate themſelves for what they then did.</hi> Something your Lordſhip did here conceive, but being ill Midwiv'd, is ſpoil'd in the production. As to what you ſaid a little before, you are as unfortunate in your expreſſions and reaſoning. For theſe <hi>Addreſſors</hi> are not ſick of your Lordſhips Megrims and diſtempers of Brain, that giddily rave and anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipate the Fruits of Royal Counſels before maturity. They, as all brave Spirits, are bleſſed with Humility, and meddle not with the <hi>King</hi>'s <hi>Prerogative,</hi> neither take upon them to inſtruct him when a <hi>Parliament</hi> will be moſt ſeaſonably called, but leave it to his Wiſdom, from which, by God's bleſſing upon it, they hope to reap the ſatisfactory Effects of theſe and their former <hi>Addreſſes,</hi> while your Lordſhip and your Factious Adherents ſhall ſit in melancholick poſtures, and enviouſly aſſiſt your tormenting Angels in your own vexation.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:104764:2"/>
                  <p>How you call Mr. <hi>Groy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>'s Oath <hi>a bare ſuggeſtion,</hi> I underſtand not; neither what credit you gain by ſaying this <hi>Aſſociation was, for what appears, only feigned and imaginary.</hi> Thoſe few words upon this account before ſpoken, may (I think) ſuffice; for all your ſcrupulous artifice will neither cover nor colour that Villany. You may as well call in queſtion, Whether that <hi>Noble and Loyal Peer</hi> was accuſed and indicted, as whether that Paper was ſeized in his Cloſet, or any where promoted by <hi>Aſſociators;</hi> you may as well queſtion, Whether that Lord ever was <hi>Lord Chancellor,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward made good his own words in his Speech to L. <hi>Treaſurer,</hi> and found His <hi>Majeſty a Prince under whom the unfortunate fall gently;</hi> Whether afterward in the Houſe of Peers he made any Speeches in oppoſition to a certain ſtrict Teſt for the diſcovery of Popery, promoted in that Houſe; Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was ſince at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and afterward committed to the <hi>Tower?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Your Lordſhip thinks it congruous, that the <hi>Addreſſors</hi> teſtifie their deteſtation of the many <hi>Sham-Plots,</hi> whereby Loyal and innocent Proteſtants have been endeavoured to be deſtroyed; and what is more evident, than that they do this, abhorring both the <hi>real</hi> and <hi>Sham-Plots,</hi> which bold and bloody-minded Factions, under the name (forſooth) of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> were engaged in to the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>King, Religion,</hi> and <hi>Government?</hi> This you are fierce and zealous to have done, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing done, you diſlike and complain of it; and what's the reaſon, but becauſe while you cry out of <hi>Popiſh Plots,</hi> and <hi>Popiſh Sham-Plots</hi> onely, theſe <hi>Addreſſors,</hi> the true Friends of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and Peace of theſe Kingdoms, ſee you involved in the ſame Plots which you cry out againſt,—and engage to defend the <hi>King</hi> and eſtabliſh'd <hi>Religion</hi> againſt all Conſpirators whatſoever, whether Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly, Sciſmatically, or Heretically affected?</p>
                  <p>But when all of you make ſuch a dinn about <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> and name the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> why do you not ſet forth what this <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is, that we may know it before we engage to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it? The Religion eſtabliſh'd in the <hi>Church of England</hi> we are ſure you would deſtroy, not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve; for this the Addreſſors promiſe and deſire to preſerve, which promiſes onely give you theſe Galls and Diſturbances. Neither will you own the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> to be the onely <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> nor with the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> the <hi>Independent,</hi> for then the other younger Brethren, <hi>Anabaptiſt, Browniſt, Quaker, Fifth Monarchy man,</hi> and all the reſt of this large Family, will take it very ill to be rejected as Spu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and unprovided of <hi>Proteſtant Portions.</hi> If you take all into your politick Ark, whether feather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or naked, cloven-footed, clawed, or hoofed, this Conjunction will make <hi>England</hi> in the next Generation, ſurpaſs any part of <hi>Africa</hi> for monſtrous Iſſue, when thoſe of <hi>Baxter's, Vincent's</hi> and <hi>Jacomb's</hi> holy Proteſtant Herds, ſhall mingle with <hi>Proteſtant Muggletons, Proteſtant Quakers, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Ranters;</hi> and your Honour's, which is <hi>Proteſtant Atheiſts.</hi> Conſidering then, the impoſſibility of ſuch pretended Union in different Opinions, knit together in one Band of Religion, and yet, that if any one or more Part or Opinion be rejected, the Project is that way inconſiſtent with what it throws out, and would ſeem, becauſe there's a Rupture made with the <hi>Muggletonian</hi> or <hi>Ranter;</hi> or whomſoever this <hi>Holy League</hi> receives not, who yet hath as good a title to that <hi>Vocabulum</hi> of <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> as <hi>Jack Presbyter, Jack of Leyden, George of Munſter,</hi> or <hi>Hugh Peters,</hi> when he came from <hi>New England.</hi> So that in time I find the League hits not upon the ſcore of Religion, but all theſe are <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> as proteſting againſt <hi>Monarchy,</hi> and the whole preſent frame of Government, and that can no otherwiſe come under one name of <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> than by joyning with it the word <hi>Rebell;</hi> and then <hi>Proteſtant Rebell</hi> ſpeaks all the Parties together, <hi>Presbyterian, Muggletonian, Anabaptiſt, &amp;c.</hi> being as the Colours of Yellow, Tawny, Green, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> by which the ſeveral Regiments are to be diſtinguiſhed. And theſe, you think meet, the City of <hi>London</hi> ſhould lead the way to addreſs for their Protection, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they may conveniently be (as is aforeſaid) united and formed into a Body that can defend and ſet up for it ſelf. But your Lordſhip is ſtill unfortunate, adviſing impertinently; for the <hi>City,</hi> ſeeing the <hi>Deſign,</hi> hath, in the Lord <hi>Mayor</hi> and <hi>Lieutenancy,</hi> taken a truly ſafe, commendable, and contrary way to your preſcription, and ſo have bid your Honour good Night, wiſhing you to ſleep for more wit.</p>
                  <p>And when <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſhall, in ſtead of Endeavours to perfect the important matters of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, ſit down and ſpin out more time in doing nothing, than other <hi>Parliaments</hi> have taken to diſpatch Multitudes of Affairs, or rather, in doing nothing but chalking out unwarrantable Rules for the Subject to grow licentious, and act as in an authorized Diſobedience, What Reaſon is there, that good and peaceable Men ſhould not make to their <hi>Prince</hi> grateful Addreſſes, for his Care of them, in diſſolving ſuch <hi>Parliaments,</hi> and ſcattering the impending Miſchiefs which threatned Ruine to our Univerſe? As an Anniverſary day of Thanſgiving for our Deliverance from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effable Calamities we ſuſtained by that trayterous Convention, called a <hi>Parliament</hi> aſſembled un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der K. <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, whom they deviliſhly perſecuted, unking'd and murthered, is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the day of his <hi>Sacred Majeſty</hi> now reigning his Birth, and happy Return; it ſeems to me as reaſonable, that thoſe days, whereon his <hi>Majeſty ſecured the Liberty of the Subject,</hi> by diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the laſt <hi>Parliaments,</hi> be kept Feſtival, in Commemoration of <hi>our Deliverance from thoſe great and apparent Dangers, wherewith we were compaſſed,</hi> while they were in Seſſion.</p>
                  <p>Neither are all <hi>Aſſociations,</hi> (as either your Nine-eyed Peruſal reads, or your diſtorted and grieved Fancy interprets them) abhorred in any of theſe Addreſſes, which deteſt only thoſe two Diabolical ones, the firſt, of <hi>the Sole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n League and Covenant,</hi> and this ſeized in the E. of <hi>S.'s</hi> Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:104764:3"/>but are themſelves pious and Loyal <hi>Aſſociations, excellently adapted</hi> (to uſe your Words) <hi>for the Preſervation of his Majeſties Perſon and Dignity,</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> now by Law eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd. But for your ſo juſtly <hi>abhorred Aſſociation,</hi> which you would inſinuate, was to have had the Royal Stamp, pray tell me where and when thoſe audacious <hi>Ruffians</hi> (who would not allow their King in the Management of his ſetled Revenues, the Priviledge which the meaneſt Owner of a Chattel Leaſe hath, in the diſpoſal of it) did agree and conſent more than in the taking the Covenant to ask the King's Leave and Liking? Or rather, tell me whether you would not firſt have taken it, and have afterward, upon the Point of a Spear, tendered it to him for his Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation and Stamp, at <hi>Holmby</hi> Houſe, the Iſle of <hi>Wight,</hi> or <hi>Hurſt Caſtle?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>How ſtrangely (you ſay) it looks, that the Mayor of <hi>Gl.</hi> who is recorded to have done Service againſt <hi>Ch. Stewart, at Worceſter,</hi> ſhould now be hugged for advancing theſe Addreſſes! From a Perſon of good Credit I am aſſured, that this <hi>Gentleman,</hi> now <hi>Mayor</hi> of <hi>Gl.</hi> was in thoſe times, with all the Family, expelled that City, becauſe Perſons of known Loyalty. But if it be as you ſay, it is not ſo ſtrange to ſee deceived men undeceived; which happening, none are wont to be more zealous Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainers of the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> which they once oppoſed. But it may be, you reflect on him, and the eminent Magiſtrate in the City of <hi>London,</hi> by reaſon of the Opinion received by many, That Rebellion is never truly repented of: But 'tis a Miſtake; for al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it be rare, yet we have ſeen divers Eminent Perſons, great in the Rebellious times, far greater in the <hi>King</hi>'s; as Col. <hi>J. B.</hi> and <hi>D. L. H.</hi> one of the five Members, yet ſince a Privy Counſellor, and Ambaſſador, entruſted with the weightieſt Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs of the Realm; and above all, the E. of <hi>S.</hi> whoſe Riches, Honours, and Truſts, were almoſt unaccountable: yet, to ſay theſe were not <hi>Men of Principles acting, uniformly, but ſwayed by Intereſt, &amp; ready to engage with the ſame heat in every thing that lieth in Subſerviency to their Gain:</hi> What is this, but to upbraid thoſe pious, great, and wiſe Miniſters of State with In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſincerity, which muſt be an Inlet to all Villany and Corruption; which for you to think, or me to ſay, were a Crime never to be expiated. Therefore, if nothing in Mens Actions and Manners doth appear, but what ſpeaks them obedient, all good Men will rejoyce at their Converſion, notwithſtanding the affrightful Blackneſs of their former Tranſactions.</p>
                  <p>As for your Brethren and Fathers of your Proteſtant Corporation and Intereſt, diſcourſe them as you pleaſe at your own Leiſure. But while your Zeal to the former Times tranſport you, no wonder you miſtake Men and Buſineſs, and dream all things tranſacted after the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurper</hi>'s Mode, as if the Country-Gentlemen, Grand-Jurors, and chief Burgers of Corporations in theſe days are like your Upſtarts, who were indeed mere Tools, and muſt be managed like Puppets, ere they could ſqueek a pittiful Addreſs to thoſe Bables of Authority. And then, you, mentioning the different Opinions of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in our days, from thoſe in Queen <hi>Elizabeth's</hi> Reign, in the Cauſe of Succeſſion, make we wonder at your either Error or impoſing Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence, if you either believe or would perſuade others to believe the whirling <hi>Zealots</hi> have not a Papiſtical Rule and Method for all they do and ſay; and change Senſe and Language as they are taught from <hi>Rome.</hi> You now all along ſay expreſly the ſame which they then; but the Doctrine introduced under the Title of <hi>the whole Clergy, Nobility, Gentry, and Courtiers Arguments,</hi> concerning the Succeſſion of <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> is wholly falſe: for, whereas ſome of the <hi>Puritan Gang</hi> (which then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be ſomewhat in eſteem with Religious Time-ſervers) did preach up, and throw forth ſuch Diſcourſes as you mention, yet was it far from the Senſe of the <hi>Clergy</hi> or ſincere <hi>Stateſ-man,</hi> who would not alter from the Pattern of Loyalty ſet before them, and ſealed with the Blood and Sufferings of thoſe who drew it, in the Caſe of Queen <hi>Mary</hi>'s and the Lady <hi>Jane Grey</hi>'s Title to the Crown. Tho' they ſaw the Danger, yet they had learned to believe in, and relye upon the <hi>Divine Providence,</hi> which takes Care for the Safety of the <hi>Church</hi> and bleſſeth it chiefly, when the <hi>Governours</hi> thereof renounce the <hi>Refuge</hi> of <hi>indirect Politicks.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And then, what a Story you tell of <hi>Aſſociations</hi> in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Time? Which had they been entred into, without her Conſent, and of ſuch a Draught as this abhorred one, which you ſo much dandle, no <hi>Ignoramus Jury</hi> ſhould have reſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Abettors and Concealers from the Gallows. And yet you preſently deſtroy your own rare Tale in the following Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragraph, by pratling where the King ſhould reign, even <hi>in the Hearts of his People,</hi> which you would ſuppoſe he doth only of thoſe who ſubſcribe theſe Addreſſes, <hi>An inconſiderable parcel of Men</hi> (you ſay) <hi>if compared with the Bulk of Nation.</hi> Pray my Lord, tell me, whether the Subſcribers in Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s time were a tenth part of the Number? Yet were they a joyful Guard to her, who having their hands, was aſſured of the reſt of inferiour Ranks, who were under the Subſcribers Command. And whereas you pretend theſe <hi>Addreſſes</hi> do proclaim the Weakneſs of the Government, you are out in that Note upon the Text; for, they moſt certainly magnifie it, rendring it glorious abroad and at home, in the Eyes of all, who wiſh the Proſperity of it, being alſo a diſheartening to it's Enemies, whether Forreign or Domeſtick. Nothing can be imagined more to encreaſe the Honours of Eſteem towards him in our Neighbours Affections, than to ſee the Readineſs of the King of <hi>Great Brittain</hi>'s Subjects throughout the whole Kingdom to aſſert the Royal Prerogatives, and give ſuch hearty Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to defend his <hi>Majeſties Sacred Perſon, Crown and Dignities,</hi> the <hi>Religion</hi> by Law eſtabliſhed, and the Right of <hi>Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:</hi> which laſt, is no leſs Reputation abroad and at home, than the former, becauſe all Diſputes and Heart-burnings con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his Succeſſor, diſturbing his Peoples Affections make him uneaſie, and frequently proves of as ill Conſequence to any Prince, as if his own Title were in Controverſie; but that, ſetled and undubitable, ſtrengthens his Power, and blunts the ſharpeſt Edge of Malice againſt that <hi>Prince</hi> that hath ſuch a Revenger of any his Reproaches or Injuries. And when the Heads and principal Members of all Counties, Cities, Towns, and other Corporations, do with ſo filial a Reſpect purge themſelves of all ſiniſter Deſigns or Intentions-towards the Crown, either in the preſent Fruition or future Inheritance, and out of the Ardency of honeſt Affections, abhorr all ſuch vitiated and rotten Members as you and others, who are, and have been verſed in indirect and diſloyal Practiſes, not only Forreign Malignity, but yours is hereby ſhattered in pieces, and you, who pretend you tremble at others, are in an Agony with the Thoughts of this and the cooperating Stings of Conſcience.</p>
                  <p>What your Lordſhip mentions concerning the <hi>Portugal King,</hi> is Forreign to the Matter diſcours'd, and more ridiculouſly introduced, than I ſhould a Petition that your Honour as a Reward for your Oratory and Manners ſhould be ſent to the Houſe of Correction.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To conclude, ſeeing your Lordſhip ſo great a Counſellor and fortunate Stateſ-man, as never to be believed or loved, never to attain to what you ſeek, becauſe your Mind's more Changling than your unſightly Body gives us to ſuppoſe, and alway knowing, that you never ſpeak Truth but as the Devil did Scripture, to corrupt the Holy to Apoſtacy; our own Searchings having cauſed us ſtrongly to confide in the D. of</hi> York's <hi>Loyalty, and unparalelled Love of his</hi> Prince, <hi>his untainted Candor and Sincerity towards all who faithfully re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect their Duty and Allegiance, your forming ſuch terrible Dangers to the</hi> King <hi>and</hi> Kingdom <hi>by his Authority and Succeſſion doth ſufficiently ſecure us from Fear: For, were there any real Danger imminent, you would never diſcover it, it being impoſſible but you ſhould have an Hand in it. And this Giant</hi> Popery, <hi>as it is magnified by your Opticks to us, is but a Dwarfe: How much pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perer he may appear to ſome, when ſhewn from off your Munkey Shoulders, I cannot tell, and leave you to the Tryal; whom I deſire to pardon for any thing harſhly expreſſed, becauſe I hope it may prove beneficial to your Honour, and if ſo, it is the ſame to</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>From <hi>Newmarket</hi> 
                        <date>March 16th.</date>
                     </dateline>
                     <signed>Your Lordſhips very Friend and Servant. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for <hi>Ralph Stamp.</hi> 1682.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
